[Music]
This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
The
question is, can you defeat the
uncertainty principle in the following
way? You measure the position of an
object first to a uh poor accuracy. It's
somewhere's in here somewhere within
some region of size. Let's call it
delta.
And then you wait a long long time and
the particle is someplace else
presumably and you measure it again with
the same poor accuracy. So it's over
here somewhere's in
delta again. How far did it move the
distance that oh and let's say we
discover after having measured it that
uh the center of these fuzzy regions the
center of these fuzzy regions are
separated by some distance let's call it
L.
All right. So how well do we know the
position? We know the position uh or we
know the separation. Let's talk about
the separation. We know the separation
is L plus or minus
something of order delta. In other
words, the distance of separation is L
with a fuzziness or an uncertainty which
is of order delta. Two delta, a half
delta. That's not the important thing.
Now we want to find out how fast it was
moving. So we divide it by the time.
That's the amount of time between the
two measurements.
What's the uncertainty in the velocity?
The uncertainty in the velocity, the
velocity is L over T
plus or minus delta / T. And if we make
t big enough, if we make t big enough,
delta over t can be arbitrarily small.
So it seems then that we can measure the
position to accuracy delta, but the
velocity to arbitrary accuracy because
delta over t gets smaller and smaller.
Now the answer to this is what we've
done is we've measured what we wanted to
do was to measure the position and
velocity
at a time just before the measurement
was done. We want to know at a
particular instant of time. Right now I
want to try to measure the position and
velocity sort of simultaneously
or I want to know both position and
velocity. Well, the problem here is that
you don't know the velocity or the
momentum as accurately as you thought.
Not if you meant the velocity before
you measured before you began the
measurement before you began the
measurement. The particle had a certain
momentum and then in order to measure it
to within accuracy delta, you had to hit
it with a photon of wavelength delta or
smaller. And that in itself will
change the velocity by an amount which
is uh given by the uncertainty principle
h bar over delta.
What you're doing here is you're
measuring the velocity accurately but
the velocity after you made the first
initial measurement of position.
that velocity is a little bit different
than the initial velocity because in
order to measure the position you had to
hit it with a uh with a photon. So
you're not measuring what you wanted to
measure which was the original position
and velocity simultaneously. You're
measuring the position now to some
accuracy but then the velocity after you
gave it a shot uh with the photon.
So it's not what the uncertainty
principle really talks about.
Okay, let's uh
yeah.
Uh yes, but you don't know the velocity
anymore because velocity right before
you hit it.
Well, you don't know the velocity
afterwards. Uh
so, so if you try but if you try to
repeat the measurement of velocity to
check it, you discover that it was a
little different. It's a question of
repeatability of experiments and uh and
uh checking your experiments.
So you're always going to be stuck in
that way that uh that
uh
in any case that is what the
what the uncertainty what the
uncertainty principle says is that you
can't know uh in this case in this case
that the measurement of the final
position over here will give a little
bit of a kick to the uh uh to the
velocity and you won't know it
afterwards. It says what it says and
you're perfectly right. I mean there's
something funny but uh but it says what
it says and what it says in this case is
you can't check that that was the
velocity without changing it by an
amount of order h bar over delta. So you
may think that that was the velocity.
Okay. I think I measured it but now you
try to check it. And in classical
physics you can measure the position
arbitrarily gently and not affect the
velocity. in quantum mechanics. Not so.
Okay. So, let's see. So,
uh are we ready to begin? Yeah, we're
ready to begin. Okay.
What I want to do before I do anything
else is just an exceedingly quick review
of complex numbers. Just uh
not because I really want to teach you
complex numbers. I presume everybody
knows about complex numbers but uh
because just for some notational
reasons.
Incidentally, we're going to be
continuing with linear vector spaces for
a while. It's a somewhat dry subject.
The that's the bad news. The good news
is it's a very easy subject.
So once you get it, you should be uh it
should be easy enough. Thank you,
Michael.
But it does pay to spend
a uh
Michael, say hello to your mother.
You're on TV.
Okay.
So, let's let's just remind ourselves
very quickly about some a property or
two of complex numbers. Not all about
complex numbers. just one or two
properties that I want to I want to
remind you of because we'll see things
very similar to them later. Okay. Uh
before we even do that, let me just
mention about linear vector spaces.
Linear vector spaces are composed of
objects which you can multiply by
numbers and add. You can add them and
multiply them by numbers. And in fact,
complex vector spaces are things that
you can multiply by complex numbers and
you can add them. That's what defines a
complex vector space. The simplest
complex vector space is of course just
the complex numbers. The complex numbers
you can multiply them by other complex
numbers and you can add them. So the
complex numbers by themselves are a very
simple linear vector space. I just want
to tell you that and then we can examine
the complex numbers a little bit. Uh
a complex number is just two real
numbers added together
with i.
x + i y. x is called the real part. y is
called the imaginary part and i is the
square root of minus one. All arithmetic
or well let's call it algebra. All
elementary algebra, multiplication of
complex numbers, addition of complex
numbers is exactly the same as if they
were ordinary numbers except you must
remember that i^2 is minus1. That's all
that's uh that's the theory of complex
numbers in a nutshell. Every complex
number can be represented as a point on
the xy plane. Don't confuse this xy
plane with any vector space. It's just
the xy plane. So every point uh in the
complex plane has an x and a y and it
can be plotted and it's usual to call it
z. It's a common terminology for complex
numbers. If we wanted to remember that
complex numbers are vector spaces
that uh that they can be added and use
the notation that we started to use last
time for vector spaces. namely that uh a
vector in a vector space
is often represented in quantum
mechanics in any case in a complex
vector space by a K vector just a symbol
DAX famous symbol that looks like this
then we might just describe we might
just say the complex numbers are
very very simple vectors in a simple
vector space in fact as we'll see it's
just a one-dimensional vector space as
we'll see complex numbers just in the
same sense that the real numbers can be
thought of as vectors on a line in one
dimension. The complex numbers are comp
are a complex vector space
uh of one dimension. We'll find out
eventually what dimension means but for
the moment let's just uh not worry about
that. Now every complex number has
associated with it a complex conjugate.
The complex conjugate is usually
represented by putting a star over it.
And it's just the same real part minus
iy.
And so what it is is it's the
reflection. This is z. It's the
reflection of as if the uh horizontal
axis was a mirror.
just a reflection about the x- axis
that's called z star.
Another way that we could represent it
if we were using the notation of complex
vector spaces would be
that way. This is called the bra vector.
This is called the k vector. When you
put one next to another, it's called a
bra or a bracket. Um
really the bra vectors are really
basically just complex conjugates
of the K vectors. So if we were just
dealing with a one-dimensional vector
space complex vector space just the
complex numbers we might easily use the
notation Z and Z star or KZ Z and braz
and they would mean essentially the same
thing.
Okay, let uh let me just uh point out
one more important property
that we will use and we'll use the
analog of it for vector spaces. The
reason I'm doing this now is to do
something in a very simple context that
we'll do over in more complicated
contexts. Supposing I have two complex
numbers Z1 and Z2 and I multiply them
together. Let's just do it over here
quickly. Uh, Z1 is X1 + I Y1.
Z2 is X2
plus I Y2.
Thank you.
We multiply these together just to do it
once. It's X1 X and Y are both real. X1
* X2 is X1 X2.
That's real. We have also another term
in the real part. That's y1 * y 2, but
it has a minus sign because i * i is
minus1. So that's minus y1 y 2. This is
the real part of the product. And then
there's the imaginary part plus i. And
what multiplies I? I gets multiplied by
x1 y2 + y1 x2
x1 y2 plus x2 y1.
All right. So here we would take the
product and separate it into a real and
imaginary part. And that defines for us
the real and imaginary part of the
product.
A very simple theorem. This theorem,
it's hardly a theorem. It's just a
little exercise.
The complex conjugate of a product. How
do you get it? What you do is you just
change each plus i to minus i.
Okay, each plus I becomes minus I. That
gives you the complex conjugates of Z1
and Z2. And what will it do? You work
your way through this and it will just
change the I over here. Nothing else.
The simple lema theorem whatever it is
is just that the complex conjugate of Z1
Z2 is just Z1 star
Z2 star.
In other words, you multiply the complex
conjugates. Uh just uh just for
notational
reasons, I'm going to change the order
here and put the two here and and the
one here.
Oh, another example, another another
similar fact. Uh
what about Z1* Z2? Supposing I take Z1*
Z2, that's a thing I can write down. and
I take its complex conjugate
the complex conjugate of this product.
The rule is just complex conjugate each
factor and that's just equal to Z2*
Z1 star.
So when you complex conjugate a product
you just uh complex conjugate
did I write it right? No
Z uh that should just Yeah, thank you.
Z2 star Z1.
Sure it is. But uh I don't want to do
that now. Yeah. Um,
another way to write it to write the
same thing which generalizes to to
vector spaces to more complicated vector
spaces is that if I have two complex
vectors, let's call them instead of
calling them by the notation Z, now
let's just call them A and B.
All right, the rule here is now think of
the B's as being complex conjugates
because they're bra vectors and A's as
being the original vector space because
they're K vectors, right? Well, the rule
that is analogous to this is that if we
interchange here, look at this for a
moment. Uh supposing we interchange Z1
and Z2, what happens to the result?
If we interchange Z1 and Z2,
let's do it right here. The this the
interchange this is the interchange
operation. The interchange operation
will turn this into Z1*
Z2. Just interchanging one and two. just
interchanging one and two will replace
Z2 by Z1 and Z1 by Z2. But this is just
a complex conjugate of this.
So interchanging the one and two or the
bras and the cats just does nothing but
complex conjugates. So to make it short,
if I take the
well, if I take some sort of product, we
haven't defined this yet, but I'm just
writing it down for future reference. If
I think of complex numbers as vectors in
a vector space and I multiply the bras
times the cats which means multiply the
complex numbers by their complex
conjugates then you just interchange the
two complex numbers and complex
conjugate. So when you interchange or
when you interchange the bras and ks
it's equivalent to complex conjugation.
We'll come back to it uh in some detail
very shortly.
It's just a useful thing to keep in mind
that the the mapping from bras to ks is
just complex is essentially complex
conjugation. Okay, let's go back and
very briefly quickly review what a ve
what a complex vector space is.
Uh as I said it is it is really the
heart of the mathematics of quantum
mechanics and we can't do without it. So
we have to spend a little bit of time.
First of all, it has a set of elements
called A. A b c and so forth. How many
of them? An infinite number of them. But
not but as we'll see uh infinite in
certain sense. Uh just like the complex
numbers, there are infinite number of
complex numbers. There's also an
infinite number of elements that we're
going to call a.
They have the property that first of all
you can multiply any one of them by a
complex number alpha and you get a new
one let's call it C.
So multiplication by a complex number is
a is a allowed operation that gives you
another vector and adding them a + b
is another allowable operation. You can
put these two together and you can say
given any two um vectors, any two
complex vectors, you can add them alpha
a
plus beta b
and get another
complex number.
If you can multiply them by con, if you
can multiply them by complex numbers and
if you can add them, then you can add
them in combination with coefficients in
front of them. And the point is that
they're closed under these operations.
See, alphas and betas can be any complex
numbers. Now for example this would
preclude
um
the
real numbers as being a complex vector
space. The real numbers cannot be
multiplied by complex numbers and give
back real numbers. So the real numbers
are not a complex vector space. They are
a real vector space. Meaning to say that
the real numbers can be multiplied they
can be multiplied by other real numbers
real constants and they can be added. So
they're a real vector space. But what
about the positive numbers? Are the
positive numbers uh uh a vector space
under the reals? No. Because part of the
definition of a real vector space is
that you can multiply numbers by any
real number positive or negative.
So uh
and that's that's it. That is the
definition of a complex vector space.
Let me give you two examples. We talked
about them last time just to review them
very quickly. One example.
Oh, ordinary vectors are vectors form a
vector space and they form a vector
space which is a real vector space.
Ordinary vectors which are just arrows
in space can be multiplied and added but
multiplied only by real numbers. Does
not make sense to take an ordinary
vector my finger and multiply it by a
complex number. All right. So ordinary
vectors are a vector space but they're a
real vector space.
All right. Some examples of complex
vector spaces.
complex functions.
Let's call it S. A function of a
variable. Now, the variable does not
have to be complex. It can be complex,
but it doesn't have to be complex. It
could just be an ordinary real argument
of the function. Argument means the
thing that the function depends on. S of
X where X is real but S is S is complex.
In other words, S is of the form some
real part. Let's call it S real of X
plus I * S imaginary of X.
That's the collection of complex
functions of a real variable for
example.
Okay, these form a vector space. Why?
You can multiply them by numbers and you
get new functions. You can multiply them
by complex numbers. If I take a complex
function s of x and multiply it by any
complex number, say alpha,
I get a new complex function.
Number one. Number two, I can add
complex functions. Two s a s and a five.
For example, s of x plus 5 of x gives me
another complex function.
So they form a complex vector space. Now
we're not used to thinking I mean unless
you've been doing this for some time you
may not be used to thinking of functions
as vectors but they are vectors in this
mathematical sense.
Okay. Another example that we'll use
over and over are column vectors.
Column vectors are really functions
also. They're functions of a discrete
index. A discrete index instead of a
continuous x. They're functions perhaps
of an integer, but maybe an integer that
only goes from 1 to 4 or 1 to 3 or 1 to
7.
Uh, and we can
represent them
by a column.
I'm going to use for these discrete kind
of vectors, I'm going to use
A's and little B's, little A's and
little B's. But if I put the entries
into the column A1, A2, A3, these are
just numbers now complex numbers.
A4 for example.
The set of column objects like this with
only four complex entries forms a vector
space. You can add two of them by the
following operation. Let's call it B1 B2
dot dot
and define this is definition of adding
them
a1 + B1 A2 + B2 A3 + B3
A4 + B4
and so on.
You can also multiply them by constants.
If I want to multiply the vector A by a
constant, let's call that constant
alpha. Again,
all I do is multiply the entries by
alpha. Each entry gets multiplied by
alpha.
And so alpha
times a column vector is just a column
vector by definition, which is alpha
alpha A1
alpha A2 dot dot dot
So you can multiply them by constants.
It's kind of obvious
that this notation here
is describing components of a vector. We
could in fact think of these entries
here as kind of like the components of a
vector. If I were to give you an
ordinary vector in space, let's say
three-dimensional space,
I could describe that vector by three
components X, Y, and Z. And if I liked,
there were if I wanted to, I could
exhibit those components in the form X,
Y, and Z.
But of course, now I would be talking
about a real vector space, and the X,
Y's, and Z's would be uh would be real.
So there's nothing uh terribly unusual
about what I'm doing here. You can also
think of these objects as functions of
the index.
If I tell you which index, if I tell you
I'm talking about three, then a of three
would be a function well it would be
uh it would be a function of a discrete
variable which goes from one to four
here. So in that sense
even these discrete vectors can be
thought of as functions not continuous
functions but just functions with uh
whose independent variable just takes on
four values 1 2 3 and four.
Okay.
Now what about the dimension of a vector
space? The dimension of a vector space
can be defined
as follows.
You can define it as the
minimum number of vectors
that you need so that you can write any
vector
as a sum with coefficients of that
minimum number. Right? Let me give you
an example. Let's take a one-dimensional
vector space. Just the ordinary line.
Okay? And we can think of vectors on the
line. Vectors on the line are just of
course real numbers. But I could
represent them as arrows from zero to uh
to some real number.
If I'm allowed to multiply this vector,
this could be a unit vector or it
doesn't have to be a unit vector, but if
I'm allowed to multiply this vector by
any real number, let's call it R and
let's call this the vector V,
then I can and R can be positive or
negative. Then I can get any vector out
of it. So it only takes one vector
to get started and to be able to
represent any vector by
in this case just multiplying it by a
constant. Now let's go to a
two-dimensional vector space. A
two-dimensional vector space and I'm
thinking now about real vectors just to
just so we can draw it on the
blackboard. The blackboard is a
two-dimensional vector space. If I give
you any two vectors which happen not to
lie on the same line.
If I give you any two vectors which
happen not to lie on the same line. Then
by multiplying this vector let's call
this V_sub_1 let's call this V2
by multiplying V1 by a constant
R1 let's say time V1 plus R2 * V2
I can generate any vector in the plane
all I need is two vectors
right I could draw another vector in
here
V3 three but I don't need it
in order to represent any vector by
summing up uh multiples of v_sub1 and v2
I don't need it it's redundant in fact
v3 itself can be expressed in terms of
v2 v1 and v2
v1 and v2 can be added with appropriate
coefficients to get v3
so the question is how many vectors do
you need
what's the minimum number of vectors
that you need in order to be able to add
them up with coefficients and generate
any vector in the vector space. That
minimum number is the dimensionality of
the space. In this case, it's two. If
you had a three-dimensional vector
space,
for example, you could generate any
vector by taking three vectors along the
mutually perpendicular axis or any other
three vectors as long as they don't lie
in a plane. as long as uh they don't lie
in a plane. So it takes three vectors in
order a minimum of three vectors in
order to be able to represent any vector
lying in a three-dimensional vector
space. And that's the general
definition. How many vectors do you need
in order to be able to add them up with
coefficients and represent any vector in
the space?
Let's look at some examples. How many
vectors do you need?
uh let's take here we have uh vectors
column vectors made with four entries
only four entries I assert that that's a
fourdimensional vector space how do I
see that well
there are four vectors
and you need all of them incidentally
any fewer than this you wouldn't be able
to represent any vector but you can take
the four vectors to be 1 0 0 0
comma
0 1 0 0 0
1 0
and of course the last one is
0 0 0 1. If you add up these vectors
with coefficients
a1
plus a2
plus a3
plus a4 and what do you get? You just
get the vector a1 a2 a3 a4.
The first one will give you the vector
a1 0 0. The next one will give you the
vector 0 a2 and so forth. And when you
add them up, you'll get back to this
vector. So the conclusion is that you
need Oh, incidentally, if you threw away
one of these vectors, then you would
never be able to construct vectors.
There would be vectors that you couldn't
construct in this way. Okay?
In particular, let's suppose we threw
this one away over here. Then we'd never
be able to get a vector which had
something in the bottom entry here. So
you need all four of them. But that's
all you need. You don't need a fifth
vector in order to be able to write down
every vector as a sum in this way. So a
vector a column vector space composed of
four entries is fourdimensional
and so on. Five entries would be
fivedimensional. Two entries would be
two-dimensional. What about just one
entry? One entry would be just the good
old complex numbers. It would be a
one-dimensional vector space. So a
column vector with just one entry is
just a number is just a complex number
and they form the one-dimensional vector
space complex vector space.
All right. So let's uh let's uh just uh
summarize that by saying
oh what about the functions? What about
the functions? Let's say the continuous
uh smooth functions on a line.
How many functions does it take to be
able to write every function as a sum?
An infinite number. Obviously, an
infinite number. There's no finite set
of functions that you can add up with
coefficients that will generate every
function.
uh if I have a few functions that one
this one couple of others it's rather
limited what I can generate by adding
them up with coefficients in particular
I'll never generate a function which
looks like this
so you need an infinite number of
functions in order to be able to write
all functions now all functions is a
huge number of things all continuous
differentiable smooth functions you
still need an infinite number of them. I
won't try to tell you how big that
infinity is, but you need an infinite
number. And so for that reason, the
functions are called a infinite
dimensional vector space.
But you can think of it simply as a
vector space with an infinite number of
axes.
It's a little mind-boggling. I I suggest
you don't try to think about it that
way.
Okay, so there we are.
We have functions
s of x and we can think of them this
symbol means think of them as we can
think of them as vectors
in a complex vector space.
Five of X
is another
vector. These are two different vectors
and they form an infinite dimensional
vector space. In the same way, the
column vectors
A1 dot dot A let's say six this time a
sixdimensional vector space can be
thought of as
the vector A. the vector a which whose
inf which is determined by the six uh
small letters a a1 through a6.
All right. So that's that's the notation
that we'll use
to describe vectors.
And typically vectors are closely
related to functions either of
continuous variables or discrete
variables.
Now we come to the idea of the dual
vector space. The dual vector space is
really just the complex conjugate vector
space. Uh that's a secret that
mathematicians uh don't let out. They
well for good reasons. It's not
arbitrary. they when they want to be
general and they want to be rigorous uh
they prefer not to think of the dual
vector space as being limited to just
complex conjugation. You can have other
kinds of operations. But for us in
physics and in quantum mechanics
basically the dual vector space means
the complex conjugates
and we think of the complex conjugates
as forming a separate vector space a
different one but related related. So
just like for every complex number
we have its reflection. If the complex
number is in the upper half plane then
its reflection is in the lower half
plane. If the complex number is in the
lower half plane then its reflection is
in the upper half plane. We actually
have two a pair of redundant
descriptions of the same plane. one in
terms of the complex numbers and the
other in terms of the complex
conjugates.
Uh it's really the same plane but we
think of them as uh two different vector
spaces
but there's a mapping between them. For
every complex number there is a complex
conjugate.
For every
k vector z there is a bra vector z its
complex conjugate. And so we think of uh
a vector space coming together with a
second vector space which is in a
certain sense identical to it or iso
well isomorphic to it uh contains the
same
well I won't say it contains the same
object that that would be uh that would
be wrong but uh they're in onetoone
correspondence they're in onetoone
correspondence
but let's suppose now
and they're labeled
if a is a vector
in the k space then a
with its arrow facing in the other
direction is essentially its complex
conjugate. What does that mean? Well,
for example, if a vector space is the
space of functions,
then the dual vector space is simply the
things made up out of the complex
conjugates of the functions. There's a
mapping between them. For every a
there is for every k vector there is a
bra vector
just as for every complex number there
is its complex conjugate. So one example
of this is the mapping of
between complex conjugates.
Well, it's always a mapping between
complex conjugates. But if we were
talking about column vectors, then
the usual notation now some of these
things are just notations. You can't ask
me why
because it's just a notation. Turns out
to be convenient. If you represent the
original K vectors by a column,
then the bra vectors are represented by
a row. It's nice to keep track of which
are the bras and which are the cats by
making the cats be columns and the bras
be rows. But the entry to the rows are
the complex conjugate numbers. That's
the important thing.
All right. So for every column vector
you have the complex conjugate row
vector and those form the bras and the
cats. This
can be thought of as the bra vector.
This can be thought of as the cat
vector.
Notice we don't put a star in here. The
star is indicated simply by drawing the
K vector instead of the original vector.
So think of K as being a symbol for uh
for complex conjugation.
Uh
all right. Now supposing we have
two vectors not two vectors we have a
vector A and its image in the dual
vector space. We have the vector A. It's
bra. No, it's K. And we have its image
in the dual space which is the bra. Now
supposing we multiply a
by the complex number alpha.
What is the image of that?
You might think
that it's just alpha
times a. What's wrong with that?
You want to conjugate it because you
want the
uh the the bra vector associated with
alpha a to be the complex conjugate of
the k vector and that entails complex
conjugating the number that you multiply
a by. So you really want to put a star
here.
Alpha star complex conjugating. This is
just a statement that complex
conjugating a product
requires you to complex conjugate both
pieces of the product. Okay, we had uh
where was it? Yes, here it is. Right
here. Complex conjugating a product
means
complex conjugating both factors. So the
complex conjugate of alpha* a if a was
just a number for example would be the
complex conjugate of a times the complex
conjugate of alpha. Notice that when I'm
speaking about simple numbers I won't
use the notation uh of vector spaces.
I'll just use the uh the complex
conjugation. So when thinking about
vectors we complex conjugate them by
turning them from bras to cats. when
thinking of them as the coefficients
just the numerical coefficients we'll
use the notation of complex conjugation
star.
All right. So keep that in mind that uh
that the dual vector space
when you multiply a vector by a constant
the image in the dual vector space gets
multiplied by the complex conjugate.
Otherwise
well otherwise operations on the dual
space are similar to operations on the
original space. For example, if A and B
are two vectors and we add them,
then
the duel or the complex conjugate will
just be the sums
of the uh of the dual vectors.
That's a lot of information and it
pretty much allows you uh to uh to
reconstruct the dual vector space
as I said for example the dual vector
space to the space of function. Yeah,
good.
Is there any significance to putting the
alter?
Oh uh
no, there's no significance to it. No.
uh there's there's sort of a tradition
of keeping your formulas neat by by
writing them a certain way but in this
case no there is no significance to that
that's a good question other times there
will be for other objects there will be
when we multiply operate when we
multiply vectors by operators then it
does matter where we put them but when
it's just numbers no there's no
significance
uh but uh
I try to keep things neat by following a
certain path pattern, but you you don't
you don't need to worry about my
pattern.
Okay, that's the basic idea of linear
vector spaces and their duels
or their conjugates.
Next, the next construction that you
have to keep track of is the inner
product between two vectors. The inner
product is the analog in ordinary ve of
ordinary vector dotproducts.
Just remind you very quick quick quickly
what the dotproduct of two vectors is.
Ordinary vectors you take the two
vectors.
Uh you can think of it in a variety of
ways. You can think of it as take the
projection of one vector onto the other.
Take the magnitude of that projection.
Let's call this B. Let's call the
original vector A. This is the this
distance here is the projection of B
onto the axis of A. If we multiply the
projection of B
by by the magnitude of A, that gives us
one form of the dotproduct. We can do it
the other way. We can take the
projection of A on B and multiply the
length of the projections. The symmetric
way to write it is that it's a * B times
what?
Cosine of the angle between them.
But if we write it in terms of
components,
let's suppose we write it in terms of
components. The components for example
along any set of axes, any set of
orthogonal axes, the x and y axis for
example.
Then if we know the components of a
let's say ax and a y
that's a and bx and b y
then the dotproduct of a and b is just
ax bx plus a y b y. So we ordinarily
write that for ordinary vectors
that
ordinary vectors now I just mean little
pointers a dob
is equal to ax bx plus a y b y what if
there's a third direction
straightforward if there's a third
direction or a fourth or a fifth or a
sixth direction you just keep going a z
bz
So in other words, it's just the sum of
the product of the uh of the components
axis by axis xyz and so forth. In
parallel or not parallel or in um
analogy with this we invent the
generalized idea of the inner product of
two vectors. Let's call them capital A
and capital B.
and we write it as a * b.
Now this is the inner product of the
kept vector b with the bra vector a
because we were dealing with real vector
spaces. We didn't have to worry about
complex conjugating anything. But when
we're dealing with complex vector
spaces, when we multiply two vectors, we
have to decide which one is the K vector
and which one is the bra vector. Once we
do that, then I'll tell you what the
well then I'll tell you what the rule
is. First of all, the inner product has
some properties. This is this is
abstract. First of all, it has some
abstract properties.
Uh
the first abstract property is supposing
you multiply the vector B by beta. So
this is beta x b.
This is the inner product of a
with the vector beta x b. So let's put
all of this in a in a in a parenthesy
here. parenthesis
that inner product is just beta
times the inner product of ab.
If you double, in other words, if you
double the length of B and not double
the length of A, then you just double
the inner product. Okay? If you were to
double both A and B, of course you get a
factor of four. But we're just doubling
doubling or multiplying by beta one of
the vectors. If we do that, then the
inner product itself just gets
multiplied by beta.
Another fact is that if we multiply a by
a sum, let's say
b
+ c, the inner product of a with b + c.
That's just given by
a in a product with b
plus a in a product with c.
The mathematical language is that the
inner product is linear
is a linear operation on on B.
These are all properties that ordinary
dotproducts between vectors have and
they're properties that you can check
for the inner products between more
abstract vectors if I give you the rule.
So far I haven't given you the rule for
inner products for column vectors or for
functions. I'm going to give you that as
examples. But before I do, I want to
finish up with the abstract properties.
Another
abstract property is that the inner
product of A with B,
K vector B, bra vector A, is related to
but is not equal to in general the inner
product of B with A.
Notice what I've done here. Effectively,
I've complex conjugated both A and B.
I've replaced A by the complex conjugate
of B and B by the complex conjugate of
A. What would you get? What what would
you expect to get on the right hand side
here?
Yeah. If you take two numbers and you
multiply them,
sorry, if you take a number times, if
you know what I mean,
you've complex conjugated both factors,
you can expect that the result is just
uh the complex conjugation. So that's
the correct equation. When you
interchange bra and k vector, you have
to complex conjugate. And that's the
rule for that's analogous to a rule.
Let's see, it's analogous to this one.
Z1 star time Z2 star
is uh Z1 star Z2. Okay, you see what
I've done?
Yeah, I think it's the first one, right?
Okay, so if you complex conjugate both
factors then the product complex
conjugates this is now to be taken as an
abstract
defi part of the definition of an in of
a good inner product. The last
definition. Oh, from this we can derive
something very simply. Supposing we take
the inner product of a vector with
itself.
Then this says that it's equal to the
inner product of the vector with itself.
If I interchange a and a that doesn't do
anything complex conjugated.
So it says that whatever this object is,
whatever this number is or the inner
product is incidentally a number, not a
not a vector. The inner product is a
number.
The inner product of a with a is its own
complex conjugate.
What are numbers called which are their
own complex conjugates? They're called
real, right? They're numbers on the real
axis. They're their own complex
conjugates. So they're their own
reflections. and that means they're on
the real axis. So the inner product of a
vector with itself is real.
Now there's one more property
that the inner product actually inherits
from the complex conjugation idea.
Again, it has to do with the complex
conjugate of a thing with itself or an a
with an a. What do we know about the
complex conjugation conjugate of a
sorry, what do we know about the product
of a complex number with its conjugate
besides the fact that it's real?
It's positive.
It's positive. It's always positive.
Let's just check it. It's x + i y
* x - i y.
The imaginary part cancels.
Ix
both terms have an xy * an i but one has
a plus sign, the other has a minus sign.
But then this is equal to x^2 + y^2
+ y^2 because i * minus i is + 1. Okay?
So it's always positive. x^2 + y^2
real and positive.
This is part
or in fact this set of requirements
that when you multiply a bra vector or k
vector by a complex number that simply
multiplies the inner product by the same
number. You can take inner products with
sums
and you just get the sum of inner
products.
When you interchange bra and k you
complex conjugate.
And one more rule that the inner product
of a vector with itself is positive.
That it's real follows from the previous
one.
It doesn't follow from anything. Doesn't
follow from anything.
uh as an example of where it doesn't
follow in real vector spaces four
vectors in uh in um in relativity
can have inner products with themselves
which are positive or negative or zero
light space-like and and uh and
timelike. So it doesn't follow from any
anything but it is part of the
definition of an inner product and a
complex vector space. All right. So what
is a um
these are rules about what the inner
product has to satisfy. Now you may be
able to find more than one construction
for an inner product which is consistent
with these rules and in general you can
but I'll give you the simple inner
product for functions and for column
vectors which satisfies these rules very
easily and I'll leave it for you to go
home and prove the various properties.
These uh four properties here
you do it by inspection. It's not very
hard. For a function or for the vector
space of functions the inner product of
phi with s
fi and s are both functions f ofx and s
of x right that's equal to the integral
dx. Now of course you have to decide
functions
over what interval. For example, we
could have functions on the interval
from 0 to 1. We could have functions
from minus infinity to plus infinity.
But whatever the interval is here,
integral of
phi star of x
s of x,
notice that
because phi is the bra vector, it gets
conjugated in here. And we just multiply
phi star of x by s of x and integrate.
Right? Easy, very very straightforward
to prove all of these properties here.
I'll leave it to you as I said. So
that's the inner product or the
dotproduct between two functions. The
integral bystar sign
for column vectors and row vectors. The
bra vectors, let's call the bra vector
B1, B2,
B3, three-dimensional complex vector
space. And let's take the row vector.
No, sorry. This is the row vector. Let's
take the column vector, the k vector to
be a1, a2, and a3.
And I'm sorry, I should have put complex
conjugates here. The entries to the grow
vector are complex conjugates.
Then the inner product between B and A
is just in very close analogy. I think
we've lost it off the blackboard, but in
very close analogy with the way you take
inner products for ordinary vectors.
It's just the sum of the products of the
components.
B1*
A1 plus B2*
A2 plus B3 star A3 dot dot dot however
many of them there are
yes
coordinates
B2 B3
the coordinates of the K vector B are B1
B2 B3 the entries into bar bra vector
are the stars. Now, I think what you're
saying is we would normally call this
vector A and we would call this one just
plain B. We wouldn't put a star there.
That's a that's a notational uh
traditional notation. The star is
indicated by the backward arrow here,
but the components of it really are the
complex conjugates. Okay. So
that's the idea of an inner product.
All right. Let me stop now for questions
because I'm going pretty fast. Uh
questions.
Yes.
So the X in there really has to be real.
Oh here. Well, yeah. Um, right. But we
could for Yes, but we could, for
example, have more than one argument in
here. So, it could be x and y, x and y,
and then we would integrate dx dy.
Yeah. But then they both real.
They're both real, assuming they're both
real. Uh, now a function of two
variables can be thought of as a
function of a complex variable. But
let's not do that. Uh, let's think of
the arguments as real. I think we're
better off. uh in most situations we
will want to do that.
All right. Now uh shall we uh take a
break for
six and a half minutes?
All right. Now now I want to
come to the concept of a set of basis
vectors
for ordinary vector spaces. let's say
two-dimensional vector spaces on the
blackboard. Basis vectors are just a
pair of unit vectors pointing in
orthogonal directions
uh which can be chosen
somewhat arbitrarily not completely
arbitrarily. You pick one unit vector
and then pick the other unit vector
being perpendicular to it.
uh
for most purposes it's usually
convenient to draw the basis vectors on
the blackboard so that they're
horizontal and vertical and they're just
simply vectors that are useful in
writing any vector in terms of them or
in taking components of vectors. Uh and
let's uh let's define a basis a set a
basis set the following way. First of
all, they're unit vectors.
Unit vectors means that their inner
product with themselves is one. The
dotproduct with themselves is one.
Incidentally, for ordinary vector
spaces, the dotproduct just real vector
spaces, the dotproduct is just the
square of the length of the vector of
course. So that's why it's always
positive among other things. Uh the
square of the length of a unit vector is
one. So
first of all, let's imagine in our
vector space a collection of vectors
which I will call what shall I call
them? I guess I'll just call them B. B
for basis. Uh
little B. Now the little B's are not
numbers. Now they're a collection of
vectors. B sub I.
How many of them are there? The number
is equal to the dimensionality of the
vector space. So if it's a
sevendimensional vector space, there are
seven B's. I equals
one through the dimension of the vector
space. D for dimension. Okay. B1, B2,
B3, B4. Now they're not they're not um
what should I say uniquely fixed, but
they satisfy some unique set of
assumptions. The unique set of
assumptions is first of all that they're
unit vectors that says that every B
the inner product with itself this is
not summed over. Now often I use the
notation that when you sum over uh when
you repeat an index you sum over it.
Here I do not mean the sum. no sum
just take the i vector take its inner
product with itself that's assumed to be
one
all right so every one of these b's
every one of these vectors b1
b2 and so forth have unit length
next they're perpendicular to each other
what does it mean to be perpendicular to
each other for ordinary vectors it means
that the dotproduct is zero. When two
vectors are perpendicular remember that
the dotproduct is the projection of one
onto the other. If they're perpendicular
there is no projection.
So let's let's write it this way. Yeah.
Okay. That's that's fine. If I take two
different vectors let's say B1 and B2 or
B I and BJ
for J not equal to I
J not equal to I
then that's zero.
That's the assumption that they're
orthogonal.
A vector of unit length is called
normalized or normal. A normal vector is
unit length.
A set of vectors which are mutually
orthogonal to each other are called
mutually orthogonal to each other. Uh
if they're both normalized and
orthogonal, they're called an
orthonormal collection of vectors.
Orthonormal collection of vectors. And
if there are d of them,
then they're a basis. They're a basis.
They're a basis of uh of vectors for the
vector space. We'll see what that means
in a moment.
It means you can easily expand any
vector in terms of them.
Uh
let me give you an example
just in terms of column vectors.
I've already given you the example
1 0 0.
There's nothing special about four
dimensions here. I've just chosen four
dimensional vector spaces for uh 0 1 0
0. This could be B1.
Let's write it out.
The vector B1
is to be identified with a column 1 0 0.
And I'll write down the fourth one. And
you can fill in the other two in
between. Before
is to be identified with one sorry 0 0 0
1.
Each one is of unit length. That's
obvious because each one has only one
entry. And when you calculate the inner
product with itself, each one has only
one term in the inner product and it's
just one times one. Right? The inner
product between any two of them will
always be zero because they don't have
entries in the same place.
For example, the inner product of this
one with this one will be zero. It's 1 *
0 + 0 * 0 plus 0 * 0 plus 0 * 1.
So this is an orthonormal basis of
vectors for simple fourdimensional uh
column vectors. This is not the only
orthonormal basis. You can find just in
the same way as I could choose these two
vectors to form a basis on the
blackboard. I could also choose these
two vectors to form a basis on the
blackboard.
They're supposed to be unit vectors. So
there's a there's a degree of ambiguity
in the basis. But
uh you can check a given set of vectors
and check whether it's a basis or not by
calculating their inner products.
Yes.
Where?
Oh yeah. Okay. That's right. Yes. Yes.
Yes. Yes. Yes. No. No. You're right.
Let's let's uh let's let's straighten
that out. I should have written
before
and I should have written that this is
equal to the row vector 0001.
Does that help?
Good. Yeah. No, that that that's a good
point. Just for consistency,
I really should have written B1 as a K
vector, B4 as a bra vector, and then
taken the inner product of B1 with B4.
Good.
I was jumping ahead uh a little too
quickly.
All right, this equation now, these two
equations can be summarized by a by a
single equation.
This is BI BJ. If j is not equal to i.
If it is equal to i, then the answer is
just one. So b i bj
is equal to 1 if i is equal to j. It's
zero if i is not equal to j. That's the
chronica delta symbol i j. Delta j.
Delta J is defined so that it's
one when I is equal to J and zero when I
is not equal to J. That's the definition
of a chronica delta. And that defines a
basis.
Now let me show you how to take any
vector.
Let's suppose we have D basis vectors.
We know we don't need more than d
vectors in a d-dimensional vector space
in order to expand any vector. That's
the definition of the dimensionality of
the vector space that you don't need
more than d vectors. We have d vectors
namely the d basis vectors.
Therefore, it should be possible to take
any vector
let's call it v
any vector and write it as a sum
over the basis vectors of coefficients
and let's call those coefficients vi
times the i basis vector
and this is just you know v1 b1 plus v2
b2 and so forth
etc.
All right. Now, let me take the inner
product of both sides of this with some
particular one of the B's.
I could call it BJ, but let me do it
very extremely specifically.
Let me take the inner product of this
with uh B1,
right? With the first basis vector
B1 with V, what do we get? Well, we get
a sum over i
of the inner product of B1 with this
expression,
but that's just vi
B1
BI.
Notice it's summed over I,
but I've chosen the first basis vector
on the left here. So, one of the indices
is just one. I don't want to confuse
this with I. Let's draw it so that it
looks like a one.
Does that look like a one?
I hope so. Okay. Now, what is this
thing?
It's sum on i. But there's only one term
in that sum. That's because b1 is
orthogonal
to all the b i's except for i equals 1.
Okay? So there's only one term and that
term is when I is equal to one. When I
is equal to one, the inner product here
is just the number one. So the result is
just V1.
What about the inner product of B2
with V? Exactly the same argument will
tell you that the inner product of B2
with V is the coefficient V2.
Now this is kind of interesting. I have
now figured out what the V's are. If I
give you a vector V
and I ask you to expand it in terms of
the basis vectors, it's very easy to
figure out what the coefficients are.
The coefficients are just the inner
products of V with the basis vectors.
So we can now write a more general
formula and uh put it together. Let's
write a more general formula, put it
together.
First of all, we can say that
let's call it BJ
V
is VJ.
Now I want you to I want you to imagine
that VJ is the thing I was trying to
figure out. I was trying to figure out
what expansion coefficients I need here
in order to expand the vector V. I want
to write V in this form, right?
Well, the answer is that the expansion
coefficients are just these inner
products. But now let's rewrite this
equation. I can also write it I can also
write of course that V that B I V is VI.
Doesn't matter whether I stick J or I
there. Same formula. And now let's
rewrite this formula here.
sticking in the V's that I've
calculated.
So let's do that. We have V is equal to
a sum.
Now I'm going to start by writing BI
here.
You asked me earlier whether there's any
significance to whether I put the VI on
this side or on that side. The answer is
no. So I'm going to choose to write it
over here.
But now I'm going to take what VI is,
namely the inner product of BI with V.
So let me just substitute that in.
BI
with V.
That's a kind of neat formula. That
formula will come up over and over
again. Sort of easy to remember. V is
the sum over all the basis vectors of
the I basis vector times B I V and I
choose to write it in this form because
later on when we when we find out what
an outer product of two vectors is we'll
discover that this has some nice
significance but this is a formula for
any vector if you know it's in a product
of the basis vectors.
Okay, so that's a that's a useful
formula.
um
which
we will draw on over and over again,
but for the moment that's uh
that's it about vector spaces. We
haven't discussed operators yet. I don't
know if we'll have time tonight. I would
like to get to operators. We I think we
will but um let's just talk a little bit
now about the physical significance of
vector spaces
in quantum mech in classical mechanics
the space of states the phase space the
space or the collection of possible
configurations of a system
form a set. In the mathematical sense of
set theory, the operations that you can
do with sets are the usual operations
that you can do. You can form the
intersection of two sets. That's the
operation. What's it? That's the
operation of and.
Now, if you have a set, if you have
a set of some kind and you consider some
subset
and you consider another subset
Then the things which are in both
subsets
are the intersection
and the things which are in one set or
the other set are the union of the two
sets. Those are the basic operations or
two of the fundamental operations of set
theory intersection and uh and um and
union and they correspond to and and or.
Okay, quantum mechanics is very very
different. The concepts of and and or
are quite different.
We're not going to talk about them
tonight.
uh but the difference derives from the
fact that the states of a system are not
points in a set. They are vectors in a
vector space and the algebra of vectors
is very different than the algebra of
boolean algebra. Boolean algebra being
the algebra of of ordinary sets of
ordinary set theory.
Uh so what is the connection between
sets sorry between states and vectors in
quantum mechanics?
Well let's go back
to what we discussed last quarter. Let's
start with some discrete systems.
The coin the coin was a good system that
was useful for us in formulating
classical logic. The coin had two
states. The coin on the table. I don't
have a coin. Do I have a coin?
Yeah,
it's a penny. Okay. Coin can be heads or
tails.
We came up heads.
And uh so
heads
or tails. The coin is a two-state
system.
The classical coin is described by a
system with two states, heads and tails,
and they form a set. That set is called
the phase space. We discussed this
extensively last quarter. I'm not going
to discuss it again. We could also think
of this slightly differently. We could
think of the coin as having a uh an
arrow, a pointer embedded in it. And I
don't want to call this I'm not going to
call this a vector on purpose. I'm going
to call it a pointer just to distinguish
it from the vectors which describe
vector spaces of states. Uh we'll call
it a pointer. It points in some
direction. And here the pointer is
pointing up. Here the pointer is
pointing down.
And I could call these two states either
up and down, heads and tails. Or I could
even give them a different name. I could
call this state plus
or even + one and minus one.
Just giving them names. Now we call
these states + one and minus one.
In quantum mechanics, we take these two
states
of the coin. Uh but of course we don't
really need quantum mechanics for coins.
it wouldn't do us very much good. But
for some very very quantum mechanical
variable which could either for one
reason or another be up or down. I'm
really thinking about the spin of an
electron. But uh but for the moment it's
just a system which can take on two
values and only two values either heads
or tails plus one minus one or up or
down. Okay. And we simply assign vectors
to these two states.
Two basis vectors, two orthogonal
vectors. One of them we can call heads.
The other one we can call tails
or
we can call them the vector + one and
the vector minus one. Now these are just
names. This plus one doesn't mean that
this vector has length + one and it
doesn't mean that this vector has length
minus one. They're just names. The
vector + one and the vector minus one or
if you like the vector heads and tails.
Okay. Well, you could do this in
classical physics too. You could nothing
to prevent you from imagining that you
could identify some sort of vector with
the two configurations of heads and
tails, but it wouldn't do you any good.
There'd be no particular purpose in
doing so. In particular, what sense
would it make to add the two vectors
heads plus tails? Sure, you can call you
can call the configuration heads by the
label if you like a k vector with an h
stuck in it and just call it that. You
could call the down state or the tail
state t but you would have no meaning
whatever to a combination like
oh I don't know again complex numbers
alpha time heads plus beta time tails
what on earth would that mean in
particular with alpha and beta being
complex numbers doesn't mean anything in
classical physics so this is something
you would not entertain adding the two
vectors together And therefore, since
you wouldn't entertain the idea of
adding them together, there's no point
in calling it a vector space.
Instead, you just call it a set, heads
and tails. And you never think about
combining them together by the operation
of addition.
Uh the oper the operation of addition
has no meaning for points in a set. Of
course, you can form the union
of uh two points, but that's not adding
uh the two points together to form a
third point, so to speak. You don't add
two points together in a uh in a vector
space to form a third point, but you do
add two vectors together to form a third
vector. So there must be some kind of
concept of a state of this two-level
system of this two-state system which is
the linear superposition of two of them.
That's what's new in quantum mechanics
that this has the meaning this has a
meaning and it has a a meaning
of a particular state of the heads tail
system which is different than either
heads or tails.
what way it's different, how it's
different
is at the heart of quantum mechanics.
This is going to take us a little bit of
time. We're probably not going to really
get to it tonight, but
that's the basic setup that the states
of a system are vectors. And not only
that, that we can add them together and
make sense out of new states, which is
for example a linear combination of
heads and tails.
It's neither heads nor tails
but it's some number alpha h times heads
plus alpha t * t tails. Now uh let's uh
and if there's no reason to restrict
ourselves incidentally to two states but
before I go on to more states uh six
state system or a 10 state system let's
just uh specify a little more carefully
the properties of the vectors heads and
tails or the properties of the vectors
one and minus one. First of all they are
orthogonal to each other. Now this is a
postulate.
The postulate is that states of a system
which are clearly distinguishable by a
single experiment and in this case the
experiment would simply be to look is it
heads or tails one experiment.
If by by a simple experiment you can
uniquely distinguish the two
configurations
then the vectors that go along with
those two configurations are orthogonal.
So orthogonal vectors correspond
to configurations
for which there is an experiment, a
clean simple experiment that can tell
you whether it's one or the other.
That's the meaning of orthogonality.
Distinguishable in the sense that
there's an experiment that can
distinguish them.
Good. That's that's number one. So we
assume that H and T are orthogonal to
each other. That means that h and t
have zero inner product.
Another rule
uh which is now somewhat arbitrary but
uh but we can uh impose it. We can also
choose the vectors h and t to be of unit
length. So let's also choose h
equals tt
= 1. In other words, the two vectors H
and T form a basis.
A basis identified with the
distinguishable states of a system which
can be distinguished by a clean
experiment. Right? We identify the
different uh configurations that we can
measure
with a basis of uh in the in the vector
space.
Nothing special about two vectors.
Another
simple system would be the die. Die as
in dice.
We throw a die. It comes up with
anything from 1 to six. One, two, one,
two, three.
This corresponds. It's on the table.
We identify this with the state. Let's
call it now. Just call it three.
This doesn't mean its length. This
doesn't mean the length of the vector is
three. It just means the vector is
called three. There are six of them. Six
distinct
one dot dot dot dot dot up to six.
Here the state vector space was
two-dimensional. Two basis vectors. Here
the state vector space dimensional. Six
orthogonal vectors all mutually
orthogonal. I'm not going to write that
down. All mutually orthogonal and of
unit length. In other words, the six
vectors corresponding to the six
distinct configurations of the die,
distinguishable configurations that you
can tell the difference between
basically in a single experiment. Just
one experiment, you just look at it and
you see which uh which faces up. uh that
uh
that uh determines for you which of the
six vectors describe the particular
configuration.
Now I haven't told you the physical
meaning of adding these vectors
together. I just tell told you though
that it makes sense in quantum mechanics
to do something you would never do in
classical mechanics and that's add these
two configurations to find yet some new
configuration
configuration which is different than
either of these H and T. That's what's
new in quantum mechanics that if you had
a single coin which whenever you
measured it was either heads or tails
there are additional possibilities
uh which are somehow mixtures of heads
and tails in a way that doesn't happen
in classical physics. The same thing is
true here for the die. You can have
let's call these let's give them
coefficients again. This would be alpha
1 1
plus alpha 2 2
dot dot dot up to alpha 6.
This is some state of the die which
doesn't have a classical analog.
Well, what does it mean?
We're going to eventually get around to
exactly what it means. But let me tell
you some properties of such a state.
Let's begin with the heads and tails.
Whenever I look at a coin
and I check whether it's heads or tails,
I find it's either heads or tails. I
don't find I mean except with the
extremely unlucky situ or maybe lucky
situation where it's I can't even get it
to stand on no way I can do it. It's
either heads or tails. If I check
whether it's heads or tails, it will be
one or the other. Right? So if I check
it's one or the other. What kind of
thing is alpha h heads plus alpha tails
tail? It is a state and it's a state
which if you measure the heads or
tailsness of it will have a probability
of having heads and tails and the
probabilities for heads and tails will
be related to alpha h and alpha t. All
right. And so this is some state in
which when we look at the penny,
it has a probability for being heads and
a probability for being tails. Remember
quantum mechanics is probabilistic in a
way that classical physics is not.
Well, what is the probability for heads?
Let's call it P subh. That's the
probability for heads. It is it has to
be positive. It has to be real. These
alphas are arbitrary complex numbers.
What can it be? It's just alpha h star
alpha h.
That's a postulative quantum mechanics.
And of course the success of this
postulate is an experimental fact. But
it's a postulative quantum mechanics. If
we if we take a sort of aiomatic view of
it that the probability for heads in
this case would be alpha h star alpha h
which is a positive real number. And
what about uh t? The probability for
tails would be alpha* t alpha t.
Well,
that tells us one more constraint about
these vectors describing physical
states. We do expect the probability for
H plus the probability for T to add up
to one. So we expect then that alpha H
uh
star alpha H plus alpha T
star alpha T
is equal to one. Let's give this vector
a name. I don't know what to call it.
Let's just call it Anybody have a
suggestion what I should call it?
H
B
P. Why P?
Well, this isn't the probability. This
is some vector.
Here are the probabilities. I don't want
to call a vector. I don't want to call a
vector by a name which stands for
probability. Let's uh just call it V for
vector.
Coin.
Okay.
Uh uh confused coin. How about confused
coin?
CC
confused coin. Coin doesn't know whether
it's heads or tails. It's got some
probability amplitude. These are called
probability amplitudes. These are
complex numbers. They can be positive,
negative, or complex, imaginary,
whatever you like. And when you add
these together, you get a coin, a state
of a coin, a state of a coin. You don't
get a coin, you get the state of a coin
in which somehow it doesn't know or it's
if you measure it, you will find with
probability alpha h alpha h star that
it's heads and similarly for tails. All
right, this object here is just the
inner product
of the vector cc with itself.
It's just alpha h star alpha h plus
alpha t star alpha t. So this is just
the inner product
of a vector with itself. CC does not
stand for cosmological constant and it
doesn't stand for
uh
what is it that you do when you send an
email message? You carbon copy it. I
guess uh it's not carbon copy. It's just
stands for confused coin. All right. Any
state any properly defined state of the
confused coin should have unit length
should be normalized. That's another
postulate of quantum mechanics that the
properly defined states of a system are
normalized have unit length in the sense
that their inner product with themselves
is equal to one. That's the statement
that all probabilities should add up to
one. Likewise for the die
We have alpha 1 alpha 1 star plus alpha
2 alpha 2 star dot dot dot is equal to
one
and if we call the state now I guess we
should call it cd for confused d
confused die then its inner product with
itself is also equal to one so that's
another postulate of quantum mechanics
the first postulate is that states which
are distinguishable
clearly physically different because you
can do a measurement to distinguish them
correspond to orthogonal vectors.
Second statement is that all of the
linear superpositions which correspond
to physically sensible states should
have unit length
should themselves be uh of unit length.
The basis vectors are of unit length.
But we should also only consider states
whose total normalization is equal to
one. Those are postulates of quantum
mechanics.
Uh
yeah, I kind of lost you there. Uh alpha
h and alpha t how did they become?
You lost me or I lost you.
Well, I don't know.
Yeah. Okay. So, so alpha H and alpha t
they became probabilities at one point.
I don't can you explain that a bit more?
That is a postulative quantum mechanics
that if you like that that that's the
meaning of the alphas but it's not the
total meaning of alphas. There's more to
the alphas than just probabilities.
Um but
as I said
it's a postulate of quantum mechanics
that the states of a system form a
vector space. If they form a vector
space we can add them.
We have to then interp
what the physical meaning is of a
superposition of states like that.
What I'm not telling you the full
meaning. I'm telling you now one feature
of such states. We will come to we will
learn more about these and we'll get
familiar with the idea. But uh for the
moment
one of the postulates is that the
probabilities are simply the squares or
the absolute values of these of these
probability amplitudes. Not the absolute
values the square of the absolute values
of the probability amplitudes. Um
It's only possible to justify these
things by showing you how they work. By
showing you the ins and outs of it and
how they work and how they lead to a
consistent picture. It's best at this
point to accept.
Make sure you know what I'm saying. The
words I think are clear that the
probability and a if this is if this is
the state of a confused coin then if
somebody somehow created a coin confused
in this exact fashion
what does it mean for the probabilities
to be this incidentally what it really
means is that you have a lot of these
confused coins all created the same way
let's be very specific now we have a lot
of coins
a million of
And we have a lot of coin tossers and
they all toss the coin or they all do
the experiment whatever that experiment
is. It's not really tossing coins.
There's something else that we're going
to do. But we do some experiment
starting with all the coins the same.
Let's say we take all the coins and put
them heads. And then we do something to
that coin. Whatever it is, we put it in
a magnetic field. We turn the magnetic
field. They do various things to it,
but not just with one coin, but with a
whole bunch of them. Each one dealt with
identically to the others.
A zillion of them. However many we need
in order to be able to use the
statistics and probability in a sensible
way. Then after having done this, we
look at the coins. I look at the first
one, heads. I look at the second one,
tails. I look at the third one, heads.
tails, tails, heads, tails, heads, and
so forth. Right?
From the frequency of heads and tails,
I can experimentally determine the
probability for heads and tails. If I
have equal number of heads and tails,
the probability is a half. If
three/arters of them are heads and one
quarter are tails and I have enough of
them, then I say the probability is
three/arters heads, one quarter tails,
and so forth.
The
postulate is that the probability for
heads and tails is given by these
coefficients here. That's that as I said
is a postulate. You can't ask me why.
You can't ask why a postulate is true.
Of course, you can ask what the
experiments which led to this weird
guess were. But uh it's we only have 10
weeks. So we've already we've already
gone through two of them. Yeah. I just
wonder could does that mean then that
like alpha h and alpha t are equal to
like 1 over two.
Well, that would be the case. That could
be well they they can be complex
numbers. Yeah. But that would be in the
case of equal probabilities. Yeah. What
it doesn't have to be one over the
square root of two. It has to be a
number of length one times one over
the of two. But you've got the
right idea. Yeah. Remember they can be
complex numbers. Uh and there are
complex numbers whose length is one. Any
number whoops
any complex number
which lies on the unit circle
is a number whose length is one. Right?
Z star Z is equal to one.
All right. So if I take if I choose
these numbers to be unit numbers divided
by the square root of two
then we would have the probabilities
adding up to one uh the each probability
being 1/2. Yeah. So you yes you've got
the right idea.
Okay. But do keep in mind that in
general these are complex numbers.
For the die, we would put a one over
square of six in front of it to uh
to do the same thing.
Now, what I haven't told you is
experiment. It's pretty obvious in
classical physics how you uh how you
make a heads or a tails. You just flip a
coin and slap it down and see the heads
or tails. How do you make how do you
construct for a coin one of these weird
states which is half uh heads and half
tails that I haven't told you how to do
it experimentally. We're going to come
back to that. Uh we were not going to
deal with coins of course we're going to
deal with electrons.
Uh but uh for now we want to get some
formal ideas. We want to get to the we
want to get to the quantum mechanics as
fast as possible.
And to get to it as fast as possible,
it's best to just tell you what the
postulates are and then show you how
they work. Show you how they work and
then come back and say, "How the hell
did anybody figure this out? Where did
they come from? What were the
experiments that led to it?"
The orthogonality of those states which
correspond to
measurably different configurations in a
single measurement. Okay, let's let's be
very clear about it.
Yeah. Right.
And this is a necessity.
This is a is it a necessity? Well, you'd
run into bad things if if you didn't do
it. The quantum mechanics would fall on
its face very quickly. But uh but let's
do it and then we can come back and ask
what would go wrong if we didn't do it.
uh given the shortness of the time that
we have available, I think the best way
to do it is to give you a bunch of
postulates, show you how they work and
then come back and say what would happen
if uh if we did something else
and uh
rather than to try to derive these
ideas. In fact, even if I had 30 weeks,
I would probably do it the same way. Um,
well, I actually think I'm finished with
the things in my notes. So, um,
we can Ah, no, I'm not.
No, no, I'm not. I'm not at all finished
with the things in my notes, but I I
don't know is have I saturated you
thoroughly?
No. Okay. Go on a little bit. All right.
The next subject is the subject next
subject mathematical subject before we
go on to its physical interpretation
is the concept of operators.
Operators are operations that you do on
vectors. Let me give you some examples
from ordinary vector spaces from you
know the kind of uh vectors that you
draw on the blackboard.
There are operators and there are
operations. Operators are a special case
of operations or really strictly
speaking one should speak about linear
operators. Linear operators are a
special case of operations that you can
do on vectors.
Uh
here's an operation that you can do on
vectors. I just draw this to to make
some axes. Take all of the vectors.
Incidentally, when I speak of operations
you can do on a vector, I mean
operations that you do on all the
vectors in the vector space. All right.
So here's an operation I could do. I
could rotate all of the vectors by the
same angle. Every vector in the vector
space rotate by 90°. That would mean
that this vector would go to this
vector.
Uh, I wish I had some more colors.
Well, the other colors don't show up
very well. So, I'll use wiggly lines.
Wiggly line. This vector would go to
this vector
and so forth. Rotation by any angle
is an oper. It's clearly an operation
that I can do on the vector space. It is
also a linear operator. We'll define
linear operators soon enough. Let me
give you another example. I could double
I could keep the direction of the
vectors fixed and double the length of
every vector. That's an operation.
It would take
every vector and simply double it.
That's in fact that's just multiplying
it by a number. So multiplying vectors
by numbers is also an operator,
an operation. And they're also linear
operators, but we'll come to linear
operators soon enough. Um, take every
vector and reflect it. Reflect it about
the x-axis. So, take this vector and
replace it by this vector. That's an
operation that you can do on the vector
space. Every operator, sorry, every
vector goes to some unique new vector.
That's also a linear operator. Let me
give you an example of a operation which
is not a linear operation.
Take a vector and square its length. If
its length is two,
replace it by a vector of length four.
If its length is three, replace it by a
vector of length nine. That's not a
linear operation. It's an operation, but
it's not a linear operation. So, what
does it mean? What does the notion of a
linear operator mean? What does it
entail?
Okay, so
two things and we've already used these
things over and over, but let me spell
it out.
An operator is a linear operator. And
I'll represent linear operators by
letters with little hats on top of them.
That's a somewhat standard notation. Uh,
often operators are represented by
boldface, but I can't uh do boldface on
the blackboard. So, I'll use the little
hat notation. An operator is indicated
by a hat on top of it. This is not a bra
symbol turned on its side or a cat
symbol turned on its side. It's just a
little hat on top indicates operator, a
linear operator. A linear operator has
the property that it
if it acts on any vector it gives
another vector.
So it gives a kind of image vector
whenever the linear operation acts on
it. Right? If it acts
on a vector
take a vector which is alpha * a.
Remember vectors are things you can
multiply by numbers. multiply the vector
a by a number and then apply the linear
operator.
Well, the answer
is equal to alpha times the linear
operator on a. So, in other words, it
just says that if you take twice a
vector and apply the linear operator, it
just gives you twice what the linear
operator gives on the original vector.
Was that clear? Did I say that clearly?
I hope so. Okay, so that's one property
of linear operators that if you multiply
a vector by a number and then operate
with the linear operator, it just gives
you the number times the linear
times the linear operator on the
original vector. Number one. The number
two,
a linear operator if it acts on the sum
of two vectors
just gives you the sum of the action on
each of the vectors separately. So it
gives you L
* A
plus L
times B. Times being used in the sense
to mean operating on.
Let's just check that for some simple
operations.
Um, if I take a vector,
if my operation is rotation by 90°, let
that be the operation for the moment. Is
it a linear operator? We want to check
it. Well, the first question is
supposing I take a vector and I multiply
it by a number. Let's say double it.
Do I just get twice what I would get if
I rotated the vector, the original
vector? So here's the original vector.
Here's
twice the original vector. The operation
is rotation. It rotates every vector by
90°. Let's say
in particular,
the result of rotating twice a is the
same as twice the result of rotating A.
That's obvious. All right. So it
satisfies the first rule that if I
rotate alpha times a vector, I just get
alpha times the rotated vector. What if
I rotate the sum of two vectors? If I
rotate the sum of two vectors, here's
two vectors and ordinary vectors
A and B. The sum of A and B is just the
resultant like that. If I rotate A and
B, the whole
uh parallelogram rotates
and A and B will rotate but so will the
sum of A and B rotate and so the
rotation of the sum of A and B is just
the sum of the rotation of A and B and
so it satisfies this rule here. You can
check that check that for yourself.
Multiplying a vector by the number two
again is a linear operation, but
squaring the length of a vector is not.
Check that out and you'll discover that
that's not a linear operator. So there's
the notion of linear operators and
here's its definition.
Okay,
linear operators are important. They
don't correspond to states. They
correspond to the quantities that you
can measure. They're called observables.
Observables means the things that you
can measure. You can measure the
headsness or tailsness of the coin. So
the headsness or tailsness of the coin
is represented by a linear operator. I
think we have to finish now. We'll come
back to this next time and I'll explain
to you how the
observables that you measure are
identified as linear operators in
quantum mechanics. And then we can do
some little examples
and uh and work out some predictions
that would follow from this set of
rules. The set of rules seems very
abstract, but we're almost at the stage
where we can make predictions about
coins based on quantum mechanics by
using the set of postulates. We're
fairly close to that by now.
[Music]
The preceding program is copyrited by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.